https://youtu.be/aE6LyX8BdI4
https://youtu.be/aE6LyX8BdI4
K. MICHAEL HAYS: There was a very important historical controversy --
K.MICHAEL HAYS: Có một cuộc tranh luận lịch sử rất quan trọng
really, an international controversy -- that sort of set the mood
một cuộc tranh cãi quốc tế- điều đó tạo tâm trạng
for the requirements or the desire for a Memorial to the Murdered Jews of Europe
các yêu cầu hoặc mong muốn có một Đài tưởng niệm người Do thái bị giết ở Châu Âu
to be placed in Berlin.
được đặt tại Berlin
It was called the Bitburg Controversy.
Nó được gọi là Bitburg Controversy.
In 1985, relationships between Germany and the United States
Năm 1985, mối quan hệ giữa Đức và Mĩ
were beginning to warm up a little bit after a very long period of sort
đã bắt đầu ấm dần lên một chút sau thời gian rất dài
of antagonism.
có sự đối kháng nhau.
The Chancellor Helmut Kohl invited then President Ronald Reagan
Chancellor Helmut Kohl đã mời tổng thống Ronald Reagna
to come to Berlin in what would end up being a highly publicized televised
đến Berlin để kết thúc chương tình truyền hình được công bố rộng rãi này
media event that would be part of the sort of demonstration
đó  là một phần của cuộc biểu tình
of the reconciliation between Germany and the United States.
hòa giải giữa Đức và Hoa Kì.
The plan was to go to the Bitburg Cemetery, where
Kế hoạch là đến Bitburg Cemetery,
Reagan would place a wreath.
nơi Reagan đặt một vòng hoa.
Now, the issue was that the Bitburg Cemetery
Bây giờ, vấn đề là Bitburg Cemetery
was the site where the soldiers in Hitler's
là địa điểm mà nơi những ngườu lính trong SS của Hitler
SS, or so-called Protective Echelon, where
hay còn được gọi là Trường Bảo vệ
these soldiers who were sort of the epitome of Nazi evil were buried.
nơi những người lính này là những đại diện của cái ác của Đức Quốc xã đã bị chôn vùi.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
- For many years now, local American, French, and West German
trong nhiều năm nay, các chỉ huy quân đội địa phương Mỹ, Pháp và Tây Dức
military commanders have gone to that cemetery
đã đi đến nghĩa trang đố
every November to join in a wreath laying ceremony honoring
vào tháng 11 để tham dự buổi lễ đặt vòng hoa
all those who died in World War II.
cho tất cả những người đã chết trong Thế chiến II.
But apparently, no one, including the White House Advance Team or the US
nhưng rõ ràng, không ai, bao gồm White House Advance Team
Embassy, ever bothered to check out the identity of the dead at Bitburg.
hoặc Đoàn Đại sứ quán Hoa Kỳ, đã bao giờ để ý đến danh tính của những người chết ở Bitburg.
Most of the 2,000 German soldiers who are buried there
Hẫu hết 2000 lính Đức được chôn ở đó
were killed in the Battle of the Bulge in 1944.
đã bị giết trong Trận Đuôi vào năm 1944.
But at least 29 headstones are clearly marked SS
tuy nhiên, ít nhất 29 ngôi mộ được đánh dấu rõ ràng là SS
and contain the remains of Nazi storm troopers.
và chứa phần còn lại là quân đội Nazi- quân phát xít
The SS, originally the security arm of the Nazi party,
SS, ban đầu là cánh an ninh của Đảng Quốc xã,
pledged allegiance to Hitler first, country second.
cam kết trung thành với Hitler trước, thứ hai là nước.
It was the SS that killed most of the estimated 6 million
đó là SS đã giết ước tính hầu hết khoảng 6 triệu người
Jews that died in the Holocaust.
Do thái chết trong Holocaust
[END PLAYBACK]
[END PLAYBACK]
K. MICHAEL HAYS: The excuse was that there
K. MICHAEL HAYS: lí do là ở đó
was a military base, an American military base, nearby
có một khu căn cứ quân sự, một căn cứ quân sự của Mỹ,
and that the sort of combination of German cemetery
gần đó và rằng sự kết hợp của nghĩa trang Đức
and American military base somehow, in the minds of Kohl and Reagan,
và căn cứ quân sự Mĩ một vài cách nào đó, trong tâm trí của Kohl và Reagan,
made sense.
đã được tái hiện lại.
This, as you can imagine, sparked an enormous international controversy
điều này, như bạn có thể tưởng tượng, đã gây ra một cuộc tranh cãi quốc tế nảy lửa
about the inappropriateness of an American president really, in a way,
về sự không phù hợp của một tổng thống Mĩ thực sự, theo cách nào đó,
celebrating the German SS soldiers.
tưởng niệm các lính SS của Đức.
And this is how Reagan responded and defended himself.
Và đây là cách Reagan đáp lại và bảo vệ chính mình.
He says, "These [SS troops] were the villains, as we know,
Ông nói: " Những [quân SS] này là những kẻ hung ác, như chúng ta biết,
that conducted the persecutions and all.
đã tiến hành các cuộc bức hại và tất cả.
But I think there's nothing wrong with visiting
Nhưng tôi nghĩ không có gì là sai trái với
that cemetery where those young men were,
chuyến thăm mà nghĩa trang nơi những người thanh niên đó nằm xuống
because they were victims of Nazism.
bởi vì họ là nạn nhân của chủ nghĩa Phát xít.
They were victims, just as surely as the victims in the concentration camp."
họ là nạn nhân, chắc chắn là nạn nhân trong trại tập trung."
This is a stunning declaration.
Đây là lời tuyên bố gây ấn tượng sâu sắc.
This is a stunning equation of men, women, and children
Đây là một chương trình tuyệt vời cho nam giới, phụ nữ và trẻ em
who died in the gas chambers with SS soldiers who
người đã chết ngạt với những lính SS của Hitler
were actually propagating the deaths.
đó là sự lan truyền cái chết.
The relativization of victims in that way,
sự tương đồng hóa các nạn nhân theo cách đó,
the equation of the soldiers with the victims, is an indication of a deeper--
những người lính trở thành nạn nhân, là biểu hiện của một âm mưu nguy hiểm
of an underlying condition, where even educated people,
của nằm dưới điều kiện, nơi mà giáo dục con người
when remembering the Holocaust, would oscillate between, on the one hand,
khi mà tưởng nhớ đến Holocaust,  sẽ dao động giữa chúng, mặt khác,
this relativization of the Holocaust as just one
sự tương đồng này của Holocaust chỉ là
victimization among others and this desperate need to forget.
một nạn nhận giữa những nạn nhân khác và sự tuyệt vọng nàu cần quên đi.
The Bitburg Controversy helped produce a kind
bitburg Controversy đã giúp đỡ sản xuất một loại
of public understanding of the conditions
of public understanding of the conditions
that required a memorial to the murdered Jews.
that required a memorial to the murdered Jews.
On the one hand, there was, as I say, this relativization
On the one hand, there was, as I say, this relativization
of the Holocaust, a desire for reconciliation,
of the Holocaust, a desire for reconciliation,
really, a desire for kind of forgive and forget
really, a desire for kind of forgive and forget
and a return to Germany's noble past before Nazism.
and a return to Germany's noble past before Nazism.
On the other hand, there was a recognition
On the other hand, there was a recognition
for the need for a critical memory--
for the need for a critical memory--
a kind of collective responsibility of constantly working
a kind of collective responsibility of constantly working
through the past as part of one's everyday life.
through the past as part of one's everyday life.
A refusal to package the Holocaust so that it can be redeemed and set aside,
A refusal to package the Holocaust so that it can be redeemed and set aside,
and the recognition that there is a social responsibility
and the recognition that there is a social responsibility
for constantly working through this.
for constantly working through this.